[music]
>> History is usually presented as a set
[music] of facts and dates,
of victories and defeats,
of monarchs and presidents. [music]
>> So, come on into the launch control
center.
>> Consigned to an unchangeable past. But,
it's not like [music] that at all.
History is the knitting together of
rival interpretations,
deliberate manipulations of the truth,
and sometimes
alternative facts.
In this series, I'll be lifting the lid
on three of American history's national
[music]
legends.
The Revolutionary War of Independence.
Is the story of the Founding Fathers
full of fibs?
The Civil War. Was it really a battle to
reunite the nation and liberate the
slaves in the Southern states? And in
this program, the American Dream and the
tall tales told by the world's greatest
superpower. [music]
>> We plotted out [music] the real story
even after we heard what it was.
>> America's supremacy over other nations,
whether that's military, [music]
economic, cultural, is often taken for
granted.
And the idea [music] that America is a
special country destined for greatness
is a powerful part of the American
[music]
Dream.
But, history's always a murky business,
>> [music]
>> and the story of how the United States
came to be a superpower is full of some
of American history's biggest fibs.
>> You [music] have lift off.
>> Lift off has happened. It's gone.
>> [music]
>> If ever an American era was idolized,
it's the 1950s and early 1960s.
The years after the Second World War are
often remembered as a peaceful and
harmonious time.
A world where moms made apple pie and
dads made go-carts. Marriages were
sweeter, colors richer, doors could be
left unlocked without fear.
The poverty of the 1930s and the
austerity of war were left far behind as
the United States soared.
America truly was supreme.
It was the American dream brought to
life. This was the world of happy days
and I love Lucy, obviously.
And America was a beacon of freedom and
democracy. It [music] was helping
humanity all around the globe.
But this perfect world was constructed
on fibs, some of them dangerous ones.
The United States was emerging as a
superpower in 1945,
but its leader was no superman.
He wasn't a war hero or a film star and
he certainly wasn't a property tycoon.
One reporter said [music] that he was
just like an ordinary man plucked at
random off the street. But this man was
going to be president of the United
States.
This is the rather ordinary looking
apartment block that was the home
[music] of the very ordinary Harry S.
Truman.
Truman himself said he to power by
accident because he was vice president
when the popular Democrat [music]
Franklin D. Roosevelt died in office on
April the 12th, 1945.
He suddenly found himself shoulder to
shoulder with wartime allies Winston
Churchill and Joseph Stalin as the
conflict in Europe was coming to an end.
But a brutal war with Japan was still
raging in the East.
Americans were still fighting in battles
to the death.
And this ordinary man's extraordinary
response [music] announced America's
arrival as a superpower.
>> Truman made a decision that I think you
could describe as the most controversial
presidential decision in history.
He unleashed what he himself described
as the most terrible bomb in the history
of the world.
>> The target was the city of Hiroshima.
70,000 people were instantly killed. The
city was destroyed.
A few days later, Nagasaki shared the
same fate.
Jubilant crowds poured into Times Square
in New York to celebrate the great
American victory over Japan.
>> [music]
>> But the victory wasn't quite what it
seemed.
Traditionally, the story goes like this.
6th of August, Hiroshima [music] bombed.
9th of August, Nagasaki bombed. 15th of
August, Japan surrenders. A plus B leads
to C.
And in this version of events, the atom
bomb is a terrible thing, but it ends
the war, saving the lives of millions of
Americans.
But in this official version,
there are so many evasions and fibs.
>> [music]
>> The traditional story makes the two
atomic bombs the critical factor.
>> [music]
>> But Japan's leaders were already
discussing surrender when [music]
Nagasaki was bombed. It can't have been
the cause.
The first bomb on Hiroshima would go
down [music] in history.
But it wasn't as decisive as it seems.
In fact, the decision to surrender was
triggered by something else, [music] as
well.
The usual account ignores the other big
player,
Stalin.
An ally against the Nazis, the Soviet
Union had remained neutral in the war in
the East.
But on August the 8th, 1 and 1/2 million
troops launched a surprise assault
against the Japanese army in Manchuria.
Russia formally declared war on the 9th
of August.
Now, Japan could deal with one
superpower, but two is just too much.
Japan surrendered.
But of course, nobody in America wanted
to admit that Russia had played this
role in ending the war.
So, the story was told that the atom
bomb had done the trick.
And that story really stuck.
Just as the Cold War got started, this
belief that the atom bomb alone had won
the war would mold America's superpower
psyche.
The United States had fought the war to
preserve four freedoms.
Artist Norman Rockwell made four
paintings to celebrate [music]
this American dream.
Freedom from want,
freedom of worship,
freedom from fear,
and freedom of speech.
Rockwell [music] captured the values
that inspired confidence in the new
supremacy. The American [music] dream
could now become a reality.
Professor Sarah [music] Churchwell has
studied the history of this powerful
idea.
>> So, the American dream didn't become a
national catchphrase the way that we now
know it until 1931. It was used by an
American historian called James Truslow
Adams in a book called The Epic of
America. And Adams's point was that the
American dream of higher ideals, the
American dream which he saw as a
spiritual dream of self-fulfillment, of
becoming the best person that you could
be, living the best life that you could
live, creating the best country that you
could create, was by no means uh going
to be measured by materialism. And he
wanted to return America to thinking
about values and about things that
mattered more than merely making money.
>> And when did it start to flip over? When
did it start to mean having a car and a
house and a nice little wife and a lawn
and a swimming pool and all that kind of
thing?
>> Around the time that the post-war boom
began and that American ideas about
prosperity were starting to shift.
>> [music]
>> As the troops came home, the new [music]
American supremacy went hand-in-hand
with new aspirations and desires.
This would be an era of peace,
prosperity,
and homes fit for heroes.
There was a housing boom.
First up, [music] a new town in Long
Island named after its builder, William
Levitt.
>> Welcome to Levittown.
Inspired by Henry Ford, Levitt broke
down the process of building a house
into 27 separate tasks.
Now, most builders aim to produce three
or four houses a year,
but Levitt's target was 30 to 40 houses
a day.
>> A thousand acres of potato fields
[music] on Long Island sprouted a new
crop.
In March 1949,
1,400 homes [music] sold in just 3
hours.
It looked like a perfect world where
anyone could live the American dream.
Were I lucky enough to have a GI
husband, the government would reward his
service with a generous loan.
Other buyers rushed here to escape the
city with an affordable house in the
suburbs.
Long Island's [music] success led to
seven replica Levittowns from
Philadelphia to Maryland.
>> The homes were particularly popular with
newlyweds. In fact, if you got pregnant,
it became known as having the Levittown
look.
Levittown came to stand for everything
that was great about the suburbs, higher
standards of living, and very very
affordable.
>> As a child, Pat Heegan experienced the
move to Levittown.
>> You'd been living in an apartment in
Brooklyn, is that right?
>> Yeah. Yes, a two-family house. We lived
on the second floor.
And uh we were really confined.
Uh we were just looking forward to
coming out to the country
and uh getting a brand new house.
>> And now you had your own front door,
>> Yes.
>> television. What what else was exciting
about it?
>> Uh also a washing machine for my mother.
She was very excited about the washing
machine.
>> Your mom, was was she happier?
>> Oh, yes, much happier. She didn't have
to worry about us. She didn't have to
look out the window constantly, you
know, to see where we were.
We had bicycles to ride, something which
we didn't have in Brooklyn.
>> You've made it sound like it was a
golden age living here. Is Is that what
it was like?
>> Yes, it really was. It was like coming
into the rainbow.
Mr. Levitt made it possible
for people to buy a house, to
have the American dream come true.
>> In this new American dream, the chance
to own your own home was open to all.
But, there was a problem with that word,
all.
>> In almost all respects, the Myers family
is close to the Levittown norm, except
in one respect.
William Myers Jr. and his family are
Negroes [music] in an all-white
community.
>> Daisy and William Myers were the first
black family to try to buy into the
Levittown dream.
The Myers didn't get much of a welcome.
Protesters clashed with police.
Rocks were hurled through their windows
and a burning cross appeared outside
their home.
An anonymous caller warns Daisy Myers
that they would shoot William down on
sight.
Residents didn't try to hide their
prejudice.
>> The whole trouble with this integration
business is that in the end it probably
will end up with with mixing socially.
And you will have
well, I think their aim is mixed
marriages and
becoming equal with the whites. I moved
here, one of the main reasons was
because it was a white community.
And that's the only place I intend to
live. If I have to leave Levittown, I
will do so.
>> The Levittowns across America hadn't
remained all white by chance. It was the
result of a clause in the sales
documents. The terms and conditions
included something called a racial
covenant. This is a legal clause, and it
was also a euphemism. It really meant
racial segregation.
The covenant stated the premises could
not be used by anyone other than members
of the Caucasian race.
It didn't apply when houses were sold on
to families like the Myers.
But these racist clauses weren't
outlawed until 1968.
As the American dream was taking hold in
the suburbs, Truman's atomic [music]
supremacy seemed secure.
But in 1950, that changed.
>> [music]
>> A secret National Security Council
report, code named NSC 68, claimed that
America's new superpower status was
already under threat.
>> The issues that face us are momentous,
involving the fulfillment or destruction
not only of this republic, but of
civilization itself.
>> Peter Kuznick has studied the report.
Peter, what is NSC 68?
>> NSC 68 is a top secret memo
that was drafted in early 1950
in order to set America's new defense
strategy. And what the uh report says is
that America's period of maximum
vulnerability is going to come in 1954
because the Soviets are out for world
conquest, world domination, and it poses
it in these stark Manichaean black and
white terms. It's the US versus the
Soviets in this battle to the death.
But, we have this idea that we need an
enemy to justify America's defense
spending, enemies with the capability of
doing you in and and and and conquering
you.
>> What, in your opinion, was the reality
of the Soviet capability?
>> Soviet capability was pretty limited.
You have to realize that the Soviet
economy was destroyed in World War II.
John Kennedy said it was as if the
entire United States east of Chicago had
been wiped out is what the Soviets
suffered. The Soviets lost 27 million
people in World War II.
They were always on the defensive in
that sense.
>> No surprise.
>> how much stronger the US was than they
were, and they knew that the US was
building up its capabilities. So, they
were seeing themselves as the victims.
>> What effect do you think that NSC 68 had
on the next 10-15 years of of American
politics?
>> It's going to put us in a permanent war
economy, a permanent alert, and we're
going to build up a nuclear arsenal as
part of this that can end life on the
planet.
>> The proposed program hangs ultimately on
recognition by this government, the
American people, and all free peoples
that the Cold [music] War is in fact a
real war
in which the survival of the free world
is at stake.
>> So, NSC 68 made it seem like the
president only had three options. First,
preemptive strike on Russia. Second, do
nothing, isolationism. Or third, rapid
arms build-up.
Now, the first two options didn't really
work. Nobody wanted to go to war. And
isolationism was thought to have led to
the rise of the Nazis. That left just
option three, rapid arms build-up. The
report somehow made it seem like that
was the only sensible thing to do.
>> NSC 68 hit President [music] Truman's
desk in April 1950,
7 months after Russia's first atom bomb
test. [music]
The report's distortions scared Truman
into tripling defense spending.
From $14
to $47 [music] billion.
The military now swallowed nearly 15% of
America's gross [music] national
product.
The Cold War nuclear arms race suddenly
launched forward.
The drive for better [music] nuclear
weapons led to a new test site in
Nevada.
It was described as relatively
uninhabited desert.
But the test site was just 65 miles away
from Las Vegas.
Where the military saw cheap land,
Vegas hoteliers saw an opportunity.
Atomic tourism began.
Every mushroom cloud had a golden
lining.
Casinos even offered [music] an
exclusive new drink.
This is
the must-have [music] drink of 1953.
Vodka, brandy, sherry. Oh, yeah.
And
all topped up with champagne. [music]
Then you drive into the desert. You stay
up all night drinking your atomic
cocktail and you watch the nuclear
testing. It's the greatest light show on
Earth.
Cheers.
>> [music]
[music]
>> People came to Las Vegas to [music] feel
the ground shake beneath their feet.
Tourists [music] could stay at the
Atomic View Motel.
See the annual crowning of Miss Atomic
Bomb.
Or enjoy an atomic ballet.
>> Put on your goggles.
Five.
Four.
Three.
Two.
One.
Zero.
>> Tourists sat on hotel balconies waiting
for a mini Armageddon on the horizon.
This was what being a superpower was all
about.
As they say,
the Earth moved.
>> [music]
>> The message was, "Don't worry."
Soldiers waiting for their own nuclear
test were reassured by the Army
Chaplain.
>> There's no need to be worried as the
Army has taken all of the necessary
precautions to see that we're perfectly
safe here.
>> What's it like, Chaplain?
>> It contains all of the rich colors of
the rainbow and then as it rises up into
the atmosphere, it turns a beautiful
pale yellow. It's a wonderful sight to
behold.
>> One of the things that's missing from
our nostalgic, glamorous image of 1950s
America is the fear.
The sirens going off.
Drills at schools. 100 million people
going to fall out shelters.
And the knowledge that within a matter
of hours
humanity could be wiped off the face of
the earth.
>> [music]
>> That signal means to stop whatever you
are doing and get to the nearest safe
place fast.
>> The Nevada tests were seen as vital for
staying ahead of the Russians.
America was honing its weapons, but
[music] also learning what impact enemy
bombs could have.
In the race to outwit [music] the
Soviets, safety took a backseat.
Mushroom clouds frequently filled the
sky.
For the town of St. George, tests became
routine.
>> Ladies and gentlemen, we interrupt this
program to bring you important news. Due
to a change in wind direction, the
residue from this morning's atomic
detonation is drifting in the direction
of St. George.
It is suggested that everyone remain
indoors for 1 hour or until further
notice. There is no danger.
>> Locals became known as downwinders.
They began to see their livestock dying.
Cancer [music] and leukemia rates
soared.
Officials denied [music] any link to the
tests.
In 1957, a congressional hearing
justified the decision to [music] expose
the downwinders to nuclear fallout,
citing the greater risk of the Soviets
annihilating the United States.
>> So, the government did know that the
fallout was dangerous, but it was more
important to them to stay ahead in the
arms race.
The downwinders believed that the
government had been lying to them, and
they were right.
This was one of American history's
cruelest fibs.
>> Years after the tests, the downwinders
were paid over a billion dollars in
compensation for their
sacrifices.
Health officials estimate [music]
nuclear fallout has resulted in the
deaths of at least 11,000 Americans.
One part of the American dream is the
idea that America is unique,
that no other nation was formed in quite
the same way.
Traveling across the states, you can't
miss the nation's self-belief.
>> It seems to me, as a British person,
that America is incredibly well branded
as a country.
>> Well, I think it probably is, you know,
it it kind of had to be, right? It's
America is a nation that imagined itself
into existence.
It is an experiment that is
built around ideas. So, how do you hold
all of these people from all over the
world with absolutely no common ground,
um no common religion, no common
language, no common cultural background?
All we have that holds us together is
this set of ideas.
>> Today, we might see that the American
dream is flawed,
but back in the '50s, it seemed that
these ideals could lead the free world.
And for some, self-belief extended
[music]
the nation's influence beyond planet
Earth.
There were reports of UFOs,
unidentified flying objects.
Arizona appeared to be in the thick of
the action.
>> Well, I heard that this is the place to
be on the lookout for them.
>> What the aliens wanted wasn't clear, but
many Americans were certain of [music]
one thing.
If there are UFOs out there, then
obviously America's going to be the
first country in the world they'd
[music] want to visit.
It's got to be America first.
This self-belief has a long history.
In the 19th century, [music] the idea
began to take root that the USA had a
God-given mission to spread Christianity
and democracy across America.
In 1845, a New York newspaper named it
manifest destiny.
Deep in its heart, America knows that
it's a special country, a chosen nation.
And obviously aliens appreciate that,
too.
In 1997, one visitation in Arizona
became known as the Phoenix Lights.
It was witnessed by thousands, including
the state governor.
He described it as
other-worldly.
He's not the only person [music] to
think that the truth is out there.
Former FBI agent John DeSouza
investigates UFOs.
>> The thing wanted to be seen by as many
people as possible. And [snorts] it was
not it had no propulsion, no human
propulsion.
There was no thrust. We don't know how
it was floating. We don't know what
physical methods it was used to make it
travel so slowly. So, this is not a
terrestrial vehicle. And there were
thousands of people that witnessed it
and saw what it was.
>> I'm
>> [clears throat]
>> a historian and for many centuries
people have seen comets or shooting
stars or ghosts. And I see UFOs as being
kind of an extension to that. Do you
think there's a basic human need to
believe in something bigger than us?
>> Instinctually people know that there's
something out there that is greater than
physical, that leads into greater
realities of what life is really all
about. And that's why people want to
believe in these things.
I mean, we're right here in Tucson,
Arizona, which is a a major major
hotspot for UFOs. And we have these
experiences here all the time.
>> I I think it's cuz the aliens will want
to be here in this country. They want to
be here in this country.
>> Yes. I think they do. Question is is
that is that good? Is that a good way
for them to go?
We'll find out very [music] soon.
>> That's on us.
>> Yes.
Yes, because they will be revealing
themselves very soon.
>> [music]
>> UFOs may choose America first, but they
might also be a barometer for a nation's
paranoia.
Sightings soared in the 1950s just as
fears about the decline of the nation
gripped America.
>> Innumerable psychologists
attribute the moral decay among our
people to the obscene and pornographic
literature so prevalent [music]
in our society.
This moral decay weakens our resistance
to the onslaught of the communist
[music] masters of deceit.
>> Some believed that communist
infiltration was the [music] biggest
threat to America.
One senator did more than anyone else to
hype the fear. [music]
>> Joseph McCarthy's reign of terror began
with a little piece of paper and a great
big whopper of a fib.
As a political meeting, he produced what
he claimed was a list of 205 names that
had been made known to the Secretary of
State of members of the Communist Party.
But all of them were still involved in
shaping State Department policy.
That was a sensation.
The next day, a funny thing happened.
The list had been downgraded. Now, there
were just 57 names on it.
>> The numbers fluctuated, but America was
hooked.
Government workers lived in fear of
McCarthy's accusations.
>> A letter arrives at your house. It tells
you to report here to the offices of the
Senate.
You have to appear in an investigation
room. This one's very often used. The
people in here are going to ask you a
simple question. But on your answer may
depend your job, your place in society,
possibly even your life. And the
question is,
are you or have you ever been a member
of the Communist Party?
>> McCarthy's team would grill subjects for
hours, hoping they'd crack under
pressure.
>> Senate historian Katherine Scott has
studied McCarthy's impact.
>> When
attorneys to some of the witnesses would
be allowed to read the transcripts of
their clients' testimony in the
closed-door session, they would find to
their horror that the transcripts had
been altered, that they had literally
been changed and typed up to say things
so that the client had made confessions,
had named names, none of which had
transpired in the course of the closed
door hearing. And in the era of
McCarthyism, a claim or an inference
that you were sympathetic or had been
sympathetic to communism was enough to
ruin your life forever.
>> McCarthy is most famous for his
communist witch hunts, but he had
another target, too, homosexuals.
>> One of the people who was picked up in
in one of these arrest efforts was the
son of a United States Senator named
Lester Hunt. They blackmailed Lester
Hunt. They tried to get him to not seek
re-election. Lester Hunt decided to take
his own life.
And
>> did that?
>> committed suicide here in this office
building.
>> That's horrific.
>> I consider him to be one of
the victims of the McCarthy era.
>> Americans were absolutely consumed by
fear and paranoia, and I think it made
people desperately cautious about their
own behavior.
There were staff members who were on
Senate staff at the time who recalled
walking through the halls how quiet it
was.
People wouldn't talk. They wouldn't talk
to each other. They wouldn't talk to
their colleagues.
Literally, they had been silenced by
McCarthy and his tactics.
>> How many people would you say, is it
possible to say, were affected by this
witch hunt?
>> I would say tens of thousands of people.
People who
believed that their secrets would come
out and so chose to quietly resign from
their positions. People who were
identified through loyalty security
programs as homosexuals and were fired.
I don't think we'll ever know the exact
number of people whose lives were ruined
by these types of policies.
>> In 1953, a new Republican president was
inaugurated, Dwight Eisenhower.
Eisenhower [music] wanted to save
taxpayers' money. He spooked at the
futility of Cold War military spending.
>> Every gun that is made,
every warship launched,
every rocket fired signifies, in the
final sense,
a theft
from those who hunger and are not fed.
Those who are cold
and are not clothed.
The cost of one modern heavy bomber is
this:
a modern brick school in more than 30
cities.
>> A large standing army cost a fortune.
Eisenhower was advised that conventional
warfare would quickly escalate to
nuclear war. So, he cut the army and
pushed nuclear weapons instead.
Here in Arizona, you can get a taste of
this monstrous new superpower force.
This is the B-52 Stratofortress.
It's really quite monstrously big.
But to Eisenhower, this represented a
bargain, cuz one of these could travel
9,000 mi all by itself. It eliminated
the need for having expensive Air Force
bases in Europe. One of these could get
all the way to Russia. And it will carry
35 tons of nuclear bombs.
This is how America would rule supreme.
The Soviet Union would be deterred from
attacking as [music] it would risk its
own annihilation.
This was the Cold War's ever more
heavily armed front line.
At the start of Eisenhower's presidency,
the US had 1,000 nuclear bombs.
By the end of it though, there were
22,000
of them.
Yet still, many in the military talked
up the Soviet threat and campaigned for
even more defense spending.
Eisenhower knew the Soviet threat was
being exaggerated by a shadowy alliance
of arms companies and generals.
He would dub this the
military-industrial complex.
Eisenhower could see that this
military-industrial complex could become
a danger to democracy. Cuz the whole
thing was based on fear. It was
circular. Threats to America would be
exaggerated. America's response would be
to get more arms. And this enormous
defense industry that was the result was
based largely on paranoia and on some
fibs as big as the B-52 bomber itself.
And something of that attitude persists
to this day. According to the United
Nations, America spends more on defense
than China, Russia, Saudi Arabia, India,
Britain, France, and Japan combined.
>> [music]
>> A new long-range weapon system, Titan
II, was also swallowing cash.
This bunker is now a museum.
Yvonne Morris was once its commander.
>> So, you'll see we're going to enter the
launch duct now and you're going to be
standing just [music] a few feet away
from Titan II Intercontinental Ballistic
Missile.
>> It's such a huge, evil-looking thing.
>> ft tall
from the top of the warhead
uh to the bottom where the engines are
mounted.
>> So, it's the height of a skyscraper
building, really.
>> Yes.
>> What can this missile actually do?
>> Well, it has a 9-megaton warhead on it.
That's the explosive equivalent of 9
million tons of TNT.
It'll actually
decimate an area of 900 sq mi.
>> 900 sq mi?
>> Yes.
>> And when you say decimate, does that
mean kill all the people within that
area?
>> Uh a very large percentage of them. And
then radiation will pretty much over the
next few weeks kill off a large portion
of the rest of the population.
>> Titan II can be up and out of the silo
in less than a minute after receipt of
launch command, hurling its payload at
speeds of 15,000 mph nearly halfway
around the world.
>> Should Russia attack, America could
destroy Russia in just 30 minutes. It
was called mutually assured destruction.
>> You have to be visible in order to be
perceived as a credible threat, and
that's what deters based on the
projection of a credible threat.
And so, the assumption is that each of
these missile sites
were targeted
with multiple incoming missiles. So, the
expectation for the crew is hopefully
we're going to live long enough to
launch our missile.
But we're on the other end of that 30
minutes where target two from here is
going to be a smoking hole. Eventually,
this site is going to be a smoking hole.
>> So, let me get this right. The Russians
knew that this site was here. That was
the point. You wanted them to know that
this site was here.
>> Yes. That's exactly true.
>> And if you ever had to launch in anger,
then you would be pretty sure
that they were going to send one
straight back here and you would be
dead.
>> And we would be dead.
>> [screaming]
>> If the president hits the nuclear red
button, they have a 50 Titan silos like
this one would spring into action.
As commander, Yvette would fire her
missile.
But she was never told what it would
destroy. To her, it was just target
[music] two.
>> All right. So, to launch the missile,
we're going to act together, you and I.
We would insert the launch keys. The
deputy crew commanders would go over
here underneath this clock. Yours would
go right there. And you'll notice, Lucy,
that the keys are too far apart to be
turned by one person.
Are you ready?
>> Let's verify.
>> Three,
two,
one, turn.
Four,
three,
two,
>> [music]
>> one, oh, release.
>> The lights are going on.
>> Do you have launch enable?
>> Launch enabled.
>> So, very shortly, you're going to hear a
loud bell.
And
>> Things are happening. The lights are
going on.
>> Guidance
>> Guidance, go.
>> [music]
>> And then, you're going to get fire in
the engine. As soon as the stage one
engine fires,
you and I have now started something
that we can't stop. Only a malfunction
will stop the launch sequence from this
point on.
And you have
>> Lift off. Lift off has happened. It's
gone.
>> [music]
>> And then about 30 minutes from now,
[music] target two
is going to cease to exist.
>> The entire Titan program was built on
the premise that Communist Russia was
roaring ahead.
The American public were persuaded
millions of dollars must be spent to
keep up.
In 1960, the Air Force predicted the
Soviets would have 185 long-range
missiles within 18 months.
The CIA said 200.
One newspaper cited an [music] official
forecast of 500.
All of them were wild exaggerations.
Years later, declassified Russian
documents revealed the truth. The
Soviets [music] didn't have thousands of
weapons or even hundreds or even tens.
They had four.
While the risks from long-range missiles
were overblown,
the next president would discover how
threatening even medium-range missiles
could be.
The Eisenhower era came to an end in
November 1960.
The new president, John [music] F.
Kennedy, appeared to be a youthful,
vibrant leader with a beautiful wife and
young children.
But the Kennedy administration was built
upon deception.
Kennedy's [music] image of perfect
health was an illusion.
Chronic illnesses made him dependent on
a cocktail of [music] steroids and
painkillers.
And his family man image concealed
insatiable promiscuity. He was even
[music] linked with Marilyn Monroe.
Most of the cover-ups were only revealed
long after his death.
But one Kennedy legend remains
remarkably intact. [music]
The time when the president's bravado
saved America from nuclear war.
It's one of the biggest myths of the
20th century.
I'm just off K Street in Washington,
D.C. It's a quiet low-key neighborhood
and that was the point because standing
near here in a boring-looking building,
hidden in plain sight if you like, was
the National Photographic Interpretation
Center.
In 1962,
armed couriers came to this building
with some footage that a spy plane had
shot over Cuba. And this is the photo
that shocked the analysts because here
are missiles.
The Cuban Missile Crisis had begun.
Cuba was just a hundred [music] miles
from US soil. The photos proved this
communist island had medium-range
nuclear missiles able to strike America.
Kennedy's generals plotted an invasion
of Cuba close in size [music] to D-Day.
Experts used spy planes to estimate
enemy troops on the ground.
The CIA told Kennedy 6,000 [music]
Russian troops protecting 32 missiles.
The reality was even more chilling.
On Cuba were 40,000 Russians and over 90
nuclear warheads.
This included over 50 battlefield
[music] nuclear missiles, each with the
power of the bomb that destroyed
Hiroshima.
Had the US invaded, it could [music]
have triggered nuclear war.
But Kennedy overruled his generals.
Rejecting invasion, he went for the
softer option of a blockade instead.
The legend says JFK strong-armed
Khrushchev into removing his missiles.
He stood tall, eyeball to eyeball, and
Khrushchev blinked first.
Under powerful pressure, Russia turned
its ships around and pulled out the
missiles.
After serving three presidents, elder
statesman Dr. Leslie Gelb knows when a
story is just too good to be true.
>> Les, what was the official Kennedy line
on how the crisis came to an end?
>> He faced Khrushchev down.
They're at the gunfight at OK Corral.
Khrushchev dropped his guns.
>> And what really happened?
>> The real story was quite different.
In the secret negotiations that were
taking place,
there were two things agreed upon.
One was that the Soviets would take
their missiles out of Cuba. The other,
the one that got hidden for years and
years, was that we agreed
that we would take our Jupiter missiles,
our nuclear Jupiter missiles, out of
Turkey, which was on the border of the
Soviet Union. And it was a you know,
almost 10 years later
that the story, the true story, began to
come out.
>> Why did Americans want to believe this
story?
>> Because it was a story about American
toughness.
And American toughness is at the very
heart of American folklore of how you
win in politics, how you win in foreign
policy.
And Kennedy proved it. And we like to
believe it was true, so we blotted out
the real story even after we heard what
it was.
>> And you yourself, Les, you you were
taken in by this. Is that right?
>> about it.
>> All your your experience in digging down
and discovering secrets and and you
thought that they were telling the
truth, too?
>> Yes, I sure was. I didn't know the truth
and I I didn't find it out privately.
And when it was revealed,
I was both shocked and
felt, of course, that's what must have
happened. How else could you have made
the deal?
>> Do you think that the Cuban missile
crisis had consequences for American
foreign policy?
>> Uh it became a myth that affected
decisions almost forever thereafter.
Uh that
the way to end these crises was by
threatening to go to war, not by
uh trying to negotiate where you'd have
to heaven forbid compromise,
which is awful an awful word in American
foreign policy.
But toughness, that's the best word. And
the Cuban missile crisis proved it.
>> After Cuba, American supremacy was
restored.
This idea that military strength would
bring the Soviets to heel was stronger
than ever.
But the fissures buried in the American
dream were rising to the surface. The
racial conflict seen in Levittown was
spreading across the nation.
And now the world began to see the ugly
reality of segregation.
White America was refusing to share
schools with African-Americans.
Black parents demanded change. White
parents dug in.
In 1960, 6-year-old Ruby Bridges claimed
her right to a place at the local
Louisiana school.
Risking attack, she was protected by US
Marshals. [music]
Norman Rockwell who brought the country
together with his popular images of the
four freedoms, now showed a country
tearing itself apart.
Less an American dream,
more a nightmare.
Civil rights leaders sent out a call to
march on Washington.
Their leader, Martin Luther King, would
speak to the crowd. Broadcast live, he'd
be talking directly to the American
people about the [music] cracks beneath
the surface of their national story.
King thrashed here in the Willard Hotel
about how to meet this challenge.
Hmm.
Should he preach in the speech?
Or should he taunt the audience? Someone
said, "You know, you have to make it
challenging to America."
But then again, perhaps the most
important thing is that it would be
inspirational.
And so, in this hotel, in this
pressure-cooker, last-minute atmosphere,
he put the words together to create a
new vision of America.
It was a new version of the American
dream.
King would do this by pointing out the
harsh reality of life in the USA, the
continued exclusion of
African-Americans.
On August the 28th, 1963,
marches began to arrive.
Over 200,000
Americans heard the call.
>> This square here was totally full of
people. They were all coming from the
station, and they were rushing up to
where the march was going to be.
>> Pleasure now to present
the moral leader of our nation,
one who has conducted a massive moral
campaign
in the southern area of the nation
against the citadel of racism,
Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.
>> That day, many speakers called out
America for its racist policies in job
market.
But it's King's I Have a Dream speech
that endures.
Nathan Connolly explains why it became
part of America's national mythology.
>> So, the march had this very clear
economic agenda, but what we actually
remember is the speech about the dream,
isn't it?
>> Yeah, that's right. The I Have a Dream
speech takes up all the air. It was much
more about the moral charge of the march
itself, and whether it was going to be
possible to in fact make the country's
stated ideals a reality in ways that had
not yet happened at that point. So, we
look back on the I Have a Dream speech
as in some ways tapping into the best
ideals of the country because it was
very effective in speaking in those
idyllic terms.
>> Martin Luther King emerged as a national
hero, an icon of equality.
But his own dream had its limits and
exclusions.
>> Going back to the March on Washington,
no women were allowed to speak. It could
have easily have been Rosa Parks,
Coretta Scott King, and you know, King
was not going to in some ways break from
the male norm of that political moment.
Also, Coretta Scott King had accompanied
Martin Luther King to the White House
after JFK's invitation, and King
basically left her on the doorstep of
the White House. So, you know, it
becomes, I think, one of the lesser
markers of King's greatness to think
about his gender politics.
>> What do you think the difference is
between who Martin Luther King really
was and this sort of saint-like figure
that we remember today?
>> Well, King's politics are very
inconvenient to the political
mainstream. Redistributing private
property in ways that would make it more
equitable. These are things that that
are considered beyond the pale in most
mainstream political conversations. King
as an image, however, is considered
essential to how anybody is going to
think and frame civil rights. And so,
immediately upon King's assassination,
you see people begin to recast his image
and his message and his meaning. People
who fled from him found themselves in
the pews at the funeral. And so, there's
a very strange, I think, meeting of the
agendas in terms of conservative and
liberal positions because King was a
problem for both of those camps in life.
>> But Martin Luther King had drawn
attention to those who are excluded from
the American dream.
And now, the floodgates opened.
>> Once you start to make that argument
[music] about equality and about the
exclusion of other communities and other
groups, it becomes very, very
infectious, right? Um everybody's going
to start realizing that there are other
groups that have been excluded.
Access to opportunity, which of course
is so intrinsic to the idea of the
American dream, was limited to a very
small group of people who all happen to
be male. Um so, a writer called Betty
Friedan wrote The Feminine Mystique, and
um she was talking about the fact that
women were miserable, that it was
repressive and conformist, [music] that
women were drugging themselves to get
through it. Um a poet called it the
tranquilized '50s, [music] right? That
people were You had to take Valium to
get through this life, right? The
failure of the American dream
very much extends to the fact [music]
that it was only ever available, if it
existed at all, it was only ever
available to a very small uh proportion
of the population.
>> In the late '60s [music] and the '70s,
American self-confidence was shaken
by an economic crisis, [music]
the Vietnam War,
and Soviet determination to win the arms
race.
Was the [music] dream finally over?
Not [music] quite.
In 1967,
to encourage musical diversity,
America's [music] AM and FM radio
stations were banned from airing
identical [music] content to the top 40.
FM radio sought cheap alternatives. '50s
records fitted the bill.
Older and wrench-up listeners suited
[music] advertisers, too.
Golden oldie stations blossomed.
>> So, America's [music]
fondness for 1950s music had as much to
do with economics as it did to
nostalgia. [music]
And where music led, movies followed.
Films like Grease or Back to the Future.
And there was one politician who seemed
particularly well-suited [music] to this
'50s revival, Ronald Reagan.
>> [music]
>> Reagan loved the era, the movies, some
of which he'd starred in, and the homely
family values.
His mentor was none other than 1950s
icon Dwight Eisenhower.
Reagan's rhetoric harked back to a lost
world.
>> Every promise, every opportunity is
still golden in this land.
And through that golden door, our
children can walk into tomorrow
with the knowledge that no one can be
denied the promise
that is America. Thank you. God bless
you and God bless [cheering] America.
>> Reagan's rise to power coincided with a
broader Republican strategy to present
America as a country yearning for lost
greatness, ready for a return to form.
It seemed that Reagan and his supporters
wanted to recreate the 1950s version of
the American dream.
>> [cheering]
>> Reagan's aim was to wipe away the
decades when it all went wrong.
Michael, what didn't he like about the
1960s and 70s?
>> Certainly Reagan's uh speeches and
rhetoric consistently would present the
1960s as a space where America lost the
plot.
The substance of that which goes unsaid
in the speeches is about civil rights,
it's about feminism, it's about Vietnam
and Watergate, but instead of sort of
conjuring the negative feelings and
[music] the contentious feelings of the
60s, he invokes a sort of idyllic vision
of the 50s.
>> So it was unspoken, but in the 1950s we
didn't have civil rights, we didn't have
feminism, we weren't having all these
protests about Vietnam. Surely it must
have been better.
>> Well, you've just said the quiet part
out loud.
In a lot of ways it's a it's a
television version of the 1950s or it's
a Hollywood vision of small town America
that leaves out all of the conflict and
complexity that we know that real life
and real history has.
>> There [music] were two 1950s,
one real with paranoia, racial hatred,
and nuclear terror.
And then there's the reinvented
Hollywood 1950s, a cozy, confident
country.
In this series, we've seen that since
its first steps as a nation, America's
[music]
had its history twisted, exaggerated,
and misrepresented.
Fibbs have been passed [music] down the
centuries from the American Revolution
to the Civil War to the Cold War.
Now that I've traveled all over America,
I think that I can still detect the
fibbs [music] and the half-truths of the
Cold War era affecting Americans today.
It seems [music] to me that a lot of
them are distrustful of the government,
think that it's lying to them.
And in the later 20th century, [music]
it very often was.
But,
lying and myth-making are really [music]
just two sides of the same coin, aren't
they?
And you can't deny that America's
national mythology
is one of the most [music] powerful in
the history of the world.